Guide to the 73rd Regiment of the New York State Volunteers Records 1861-1868 (bulk 1862-1864) MS 670.19
New-York Historical Society
73rd Regiment of the New York State Volunteers records
1861-1868 (bulk 1862-1864)
New-York Historical Society
MS 670.19
0.417 Linear feet (1 box)
This collection contains documents related to the 73rd Regiment of the New York State Volunteers during the American Civil War. The documents in the collection include muster rolls, various forms, and correspondence. The 73rd Regiment was also known as the 2nd Fire Zouaves, or the 4th Regiment, Excelsior Brigade. The materials in this collection have been digitized and are available online to on-site researchers and to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via EBSCOhost.
Provenance
Purchased from R. McCollough in 1938.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Related Material at the New-York Historical Society
The N-YHS Library's collection also contains an Orderly Book for the 73rd New York State Volunteer Infantry and a broadside dedicated to the 2nd Fire Zouaves.
Additionally, the library has an extensive collection of Civil War materials, which can be searched using the online catalog.
Historical Note
The 73rd Regiment of New York State Volunteers was an infantry regiment of the Union Army recruited primarily from New York City. Due to its large number of recruits from the New York fire department, the regiment was also known as the 2nd Fire Zouaves. In 1862 the regiment was assigned as the 4th Regiment of Gen. Sickles' Excelsior brigade. The regiment participated in many major Civil War battles, including Gettysburg, where it is honored with a monument.
Mustered in: 1861
Mustered out: June 29, 1865
Total enrollment: 1,326
Total losses: 229 (153 from wounds; 76 from accident, imprisonment, or disease)
Major engagements: Siege of Yorktown, Battle of Williamsburg, Battle of Seven Pines, Battle of Glendale, Battle of Malvern Hill, Seven Days Battles, Second Battle of Bull Run, Battle of Bristoe Station, Battle of Chancellorsville, Battle of Gettysburg, Battle of the Wilderness, Battle of Spottsylvania Court House
Colonels: William R. Brewster, Michael W. Burns, James Fairman
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains documents related to the 73rd Regiment of the New York State Volunteers during the American Civil War. The documents in the collection include muster rolls, forms, certificates, and correspondence. The materials in this collection have been digitized and are available online to on-site researchers and to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via EBSCOhost.
The majority of the forms and correspondence in the collection deal with Ordnance and Ordnance stores, including Receipts for Issues, Invoices of Stores, Certificates of Destroyed or Abandoned Stores, Quarterly Returns, and documents concerning the settlement of Returns.
The collection includes certificates of appointment and of discharge. The majority of the certificates of appointment are for Michael W. Burns, who commanded the 73rd Regiment at the Battle of Gettysburg and was appointed Colonel in 1864.
Assorted documents and correspondence in the collection include letters to Michael W. Burns, a stock certificate, a copy of an address by Gen. Sickles, a mock proclamation, and a program for a show by The Libby Prison Minstrels.
References
Stone Sentinels. "73th New York Infantry Regiment." Accessed July 18, 2012. http://www.gettysburg.stonesentinels.com/NY/73NY.php
National Park Service. "Gettysburg: The Army of the Potomac at Gettysburg." Accessed July 18, 2012. http://www.nps.gov/gett/historyculture/aop-orderofbattle.htm
National Park Service. "Civil War: 73rd Regiment, New York Infantry." Accessed July 18, 2012. http://www.nps.gov/civilwar/search-regiments-detail.htm?regiment_id=UNY0073RI
The Union Army; A History of Military Affairs in the Loyal States, 1861-65 -- Records of the Regiments in the Union Army -- Cyclopedia of Battles -- Memoirs of Commanders and Soldiers. Madison, Wis: Federal Pub. Co, 1908.
New York (State) -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Regimental histories.; New York (State) -- Militia -- Muster rolls.; Correspondence.; Programs (documents); Receipts (financial records); Military records.; Commissions (orders for works).; Stock certificates.; Certificates.; Fire fighters; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; Sickles, Daniel Edgar, 1825-1914 -- Portraits; United States. Army -- Ordnance and ordnance stores; United States. Army. New York Infantry Regiment, 73rd (1861-1865)
- Series I: Muster rolls, 1863
  Scope and Content Note
  The Muster Rolls series consists of muster rolls for the 73rd Regiment from 1863. The series includes muster rolls for Companies A-D, F-I, and K from February to April, and muster rolls for Companies A-I, and K from August to October and from October to December.
  - Muster rolls, 1863 February-April, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Muster rolls, 1863 August-October (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Muster rolls, 1863 October-December (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series II: Ordnances and stores, 1862-1868
  The Ordnances and Stores series includes various forms and correspondence relating to the ordnances and stores of the 73rd Regiment. The series includes receipts, issues, returns, certificates of destroyed or abandoned goods, and documents relating to the settlement of returns. The Settlement of Returns folder contains correspondence and forms concerning the settlement of returns for the 73rd Regiment, including letters from the Ordnance Office of the War Department, letters from the Auditor's Office of the Treasury Department, and Statements of Discrepancies.
  - Receipts for issues, 1862-1864 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Invoices of stores, 1862-1864 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Abstracts of issues, expenditures, and receipts, 1862-1864 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Destroyed or abandoned stores, books, papers, and records, 1862-1863 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Quarterly returns of ordnance, 1862-1864 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Settlement of returns, 1863-1868 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ordnances and stores - miscellaneous documents and correspondence, 1863-1864 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series III: Certificates, 1861-1865
  The Certificates series includes certificates of appointment and certificates of discharge. The majority of the certificates of appointment are for Michael W. Burns.
  - Certificates of appointment, 1861-1864 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Certificates of discharge, 1864-1865 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series IV: Miscellaneous documents and correspondence, 1862-1868
  The Miscellaneous Documents and Correspondence series includes documents and correspondence related to the 73rd Regiment. The majority of the correspondence is by or to Michael W. Burns. Assorted documents include a stock certificate for M.W. Burns, a copy of an address by Gen. Sickles, a mock proclamation, and a program for a show by The Libby Prison Minstrels.
  - Correspondence, proclamations, addresses, 1862-1865, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Ephemera, 1863-1868 (Box 1, Folder 14)